Finding aid to the Ruth Herschberger papers SSC.MS.00280
Sophia Smith Collection
Ruth Herschberger papers
1861-2005
Sophia Smith Collection
Herschberger, Ruth, 1917-
SSC.MS.00280
49 boxes (59.25 linear feet)
Poet; Playwright; Author. Manuscript of Adam's Rib (including revisions; and Norwegian and Swedish editions); and The Old Sex and the New; published books, articles and poetry; unpublished writings. Major themes in the collection include literature, sexuality, and the women's movement.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access: Accession #s 90S-29, 90S-39, and 90S-54 are open. Boxes 1-6 of Acc. 08S-19 are open. Rest of this accession (boxes 6-45) is closed due to preservation issues. Portions of collection are stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was gifted by Susan J Forbes from 1990-2016. The collection accession numbers are 90S-29, 90S-39, 90S-54, 08S-19, 08S-90, 16S-24.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Philipse Manor, NY, 1917; grew up in Chicago; attended University of Chicago, 1935-38; Black Mountain College, North Carolina, 1938-39; studied theatre and poetry at U. Michigan, 1941; and playwrighting at the Dramatic Workshop of the New School for Social Research, New York City, 1942-43. Wrote and produced plays for stage and radio; published book of feminist essays, Adam's Rib, under pseudonym Josephine Lang Staff, in England, 1948; published 2 books of poetry and contributed to anthologies; has received several awards for poetry. Participated in women's liberation movement of the 1970s; lived at Yaddo, Taos and Ossabau Writers' Colonies; resided for many years in Westbeth artists' residence, Greenwich Village. Herschberger died October 14, 2014.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Scope and Contents
Manuscript of Adam's Rib (including revisions; and Norwegian and Swedish editions); and The Old Sex and the New; published books, articles and poetry; unpublished writings. Major themes in the collection include literature, sexuality, and the women's movement.
Dramatists, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Women poets, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Feminism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Manuscripts; Periodicals; articles; Appointment books; Audiotapes; Books; Cartoons; Certificate of literacy; clippings; correspondence; Death certificate; diaries; Financial records; memorabilia; Negatives; notebooks; Notes; Phonograph records; photograph albums; photographs; Plays; Playbills; Poems; Posters; Prescriptions; Receipts; Royalties statements; Sound recordings; Typescripts; Videotapes; Writings; Herschberger, Ruth, 1917-; Herschberger, Ruth; Forbes, Susan J.; Herschberger, Ruth; Forbes, Susan J.
- Ruth Herschberger diaries over fifty-three years, correspondence, writings and other materials, 1861-2005; 2008-S-0019; Forbes, Susan J.; 57.5 linear feet (45 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restrictions designated by the donor: The restrictions applied to the accession record are the same as those applied at the collection-level. Restrictions designated by the SSC: The restrictions applied to the accession record are the same as those applied at the collection-level.
  Forbes, Susan J.
  - Diaries, 1929 August - 2004 July; 2008-S-0019 (Box 1, 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6)
    General
    Diaries from age fourteen to eighty-seven contain entries about life as an alcoholic, relationships with lovers, financial struggles as a writer without a steady income, and descent into difficulties relating to old age.
  - Family photographs, 1899-1948; 1943-1948; udated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 6)
  - Grandmother Matilda Charity Miller Eberhart annotated diaries, correspondence, account of trip to Cuba, 1861-1864; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 6)
  - Family correspondence, 1869-1879; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 6)
  - Story by unidentified owner, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 6)
  - Writing fragment, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1948-2000; 2008-S-0019 (Box 7)
  - Poems by Herschberger and others, 1972; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 7)
  - Feminism fliers, 1976; 2008-0019 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 2000; 2008-S-0019 (Box 7)
  - Tape recorder and six unlabeled audio-cassettes, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 7)
  - "Ruth Herschberger" open-reel tape, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 7)
  - Herschberger poems, 1940; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 8)
  - Publications containing Herschberger poems, 1942-1976; 2008-S-0019 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 8)
  - Personal financial information including bills and bank statements, 1990-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous articles, fliers, clippings, 1980-2000; 2008-S-0019 (Box 9, Box 10)
  - Personal financial documents, 1990-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 9, Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1972; 2008-S-0019 (Box 9, Box 10)
  - Feminism clippings and pamplets, 1970-1979; 2008-S-0019 (Box 9, Box 10)
  - Herschberger essays, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 9, Box 10)
  - Snapshots of unidentified people and events, 1970-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 11, Box 12)
  - Poems by Herschberger and others, 1980-1989; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 12)
  - Personal financial documents, 1999-2000; 2008-S-0019 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1979; 2008-S-0019 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1969; 2008-S-0019 (Box 13)
  - Herschberger poems, 1960-1969; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1930-1959; 2008-S-0019 (Box 13)
  - Fliers from gay and lesbian fights, 1985; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 13)
  - Herschberger essays, 1930-1939; 2008-S-0019 (Box 13)
  - University of Chicago syllabi, 1930-1939; 2008-S-0019 (Box 13)
  - "Alice's Recording of Stuff" and other 8mm films, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 13)
  - "Westbeth," ""Island" and 38 other 8mm films, 1976-1981; 2008-S-0019 (14)
  - Miscellaneous audio cassettes, undated; 2008-S-0019 (14)
  - Newspapers and clippings, 1960-1969; 2008-S-0019 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1969; 2008-S-0019 (Box 15)
  - Herschberger published poems, 1948; 2008-S-0019 (Box 15)
  - Five copies of "Adams Rib" in several languages, 1948; 2008-S-0019 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous book and publication containing writings by Herschberger, 1950-1979; 2008-S-0019 (Box 15)
  - Books containing writings by Herschberger, 1950-1979; 2008-S-0019 (Box 16)
  - Herschberger poems and poem drafts, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 17, Box 18)
  - Photographs of Herschberger and others, 1980; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 17, Box 18)
  - Personal medical and financial materials, 2002-2006; 2008-S-0019 (Box 17, Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1940-2008; 2008-S-0019 (Box 17, Box 18)
  - Personal calendars, 1996-2005; 2008-S-0019 (Box 17, Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous articles, fliers, clippings and other materials, 1990-2008; 2008-S-0019 (Box 17, Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1959; 2008-S-0019 (Box 19)
  - Herschberger poems and drafts of poems, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 19)
  - Poem drafts and typescripts, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - Herschberger miscellaneous writings, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - Herschberger reading at Guggenheim Museum open reel tape, 1968; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - Unlabeled microcassette, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - Books by various authors, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - Four-volume publication "Scripts", 1971-1972; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - Prescription pills, eyeglasses, binoculars and miscellaneous memorabilia, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 21)
  - Herschberger drafts, notes, typescripts of essays and poems, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1950-2008; 2008-S-0019 (Box 22)
  - Articles, fliers, clippings and miscellaneous materials, 2000-2008; 2008-S-0019 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1959; 2008-S-0019 (Box 23)
  - Personal and other medical information, 1990-2008; 2008-S-0019 (Box 23)
  - Theatre programs and brochures, 1950-1959; 2008-S-0019 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 24)
  - Poems by Herschberger and others, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous articles and clippings, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 24)
  - Play scripts by various authors, 1930-1939; 2008-S-0019 (Box 25)
  - Herschberger poems, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 25)
  - "Penny's Thursday," "Sting," "Roxy Music Greatest Hits" audiocassettes, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 25)
  - Five vinyl LPs including opera and Christmas music, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 25)
  - Herschberger poems, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1959; 1990-2008; 2008-S-0019 (Box 26)
  - Herschberger essays, 1930-1939; 2008-S-0019 (Box 26)
  - Herschberger poems, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Seven unlabeled audio-cassettes, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Herschberger's "Adam's Rib" and "Love and Nature Poems", 1948; 1969; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Bills, receipts, cancelled checks, 1990-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous articles, fliers, clippings, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Herschberger will, 1988; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Unidentified photographs of individuals and events, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Books by various authors, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Herschberg play scripts, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 28)
  - Unlabeled 8 mm film, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 28)
  - Clippings, articles and other materialism regarding feminism, 1970-1979; 2008-S-0019 (Box 28)
  - Drafts and typescripts of poems and other writings, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - Open reel tape of Herschberger reading at Guggenheim Museum, undated; 2008-S-009-19 (Box 20)
  - Unlabeled microcassette, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - Books by various authors, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - "Scripts" publication, 1971-1972; 2008-S-0019 (Box 20)
  - Eyeglasses, binoculars, and other artifacts, 2000-2009; 2008-S-0019 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 1950-2009; 2008-S-0019 (Box 22)
  - Articles, fliers, brochures and miscellaneous materials, 2000-2009; 2008-S-0019 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1959; 2008-S-0019 (Box 23)
  - Personal medical documents and related materials, 1990-2009; 2008-S-0019 (Box 23)
  - Theater programs and brochures, 1950-1959; 2008-S-0019 (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 24)
  - Poems by Herschberger and others, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 24)
  - Articles and clippings on various topics, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 24)
  - Play scripts, 1930-1939; 2008-S-0019 (Box 25)
    According to original box list, some scripts are "possibly by Herschberger"
  - Audiocasettes "Penny's Thursday," "Sting," and "Roxy Music Greatest Hits", undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 25)
  - Vinyl Ls "Othello," " Rigoletto," "Little Marcy Sings Sunday school Songs," Great Songs of Christmas," and "Airforce" by Ginger Baker, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 25)
  - Poems, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1959; 1990-2009; 2008-S-0019 (Box 26)
  - Essays, 1930-1939; 2008-S-0019 (Box 26)
  - Poems, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Seven unlabeled audiocassettes, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Herschberger published writings "Adams Rib" and "Love and Nature Poems", 1948; 1969; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous financial materials, 1990-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Articles, fliers, brochures and miscellaneous materials, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Herschberger's will, 1988; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Photographs of unidentified individuals and events, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 27)
  - Playscripts, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 28)
  - Unlabeled 8mmfil, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 28)
  - Helical scan videos "Practice Ruth" and "Helene D.", 1973; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 28)
  - Clippings, articles and other printed matter on faminism, 1970-1979; 2008-S-0019 (29)
  - Note cards regarding female sexuality for "Adam's Rib.", undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 28)
  - Pages from "Adam's Rib", undated; 2008-S-0019 (29)
  - Veteran Feminists of America correspondence and clippings, 1997; 2008-S-0019 (29)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1949; 2008-S-0019 (29)
  - Book "The Story of the Pennsylvania Dutch, 1943; 2008-S-0019 (29)
  - Play scripts, poems with drafts, essays with drafts by Herschberger, 1949-1969; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 30)
  - Unidentified photographs, 1986; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 30)
  - Various receipts, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 30)
  - First edition "Antheil" by Ezra Pound, 1924; 2008-S-0019 (Box 30)
  - Sergei Herscovici photographs, corresondence, biographical information, 1970-1989; 2008-S-0091 (Box 30)
  - Photographs of unidentified women in hospital beds, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 30)
  - Unlabeled audiocassette tape, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 30)
  - Herschberger application to University of Chicago, 1934; 2008-S-0019 (Box 31)
  - Herschberger University of Chicago essays, notes, syllabi, 1935-1939; 2008-S-0019 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence, 1951-2004; 2008-S-0019 (Box 32)
  - Poems and other Herschberger writings with notes and drafts, 1990-2010; 2008-S-0019 (Box 32)
  - Appointment books, 1973-1988; 2008-S-0019 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence and notes, 1970-2010; 2008-S-0019 (Box 33)
  - Writings and related correspondence by Herschberger and others, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 33)
  - Articles, fliers, miscellaneous materials, 1990-2010; 2008-S-0019 (Box 34)
  - Poems including notes and drafts, 2000-2010; 2008-S-0019 (Box 34)
  - Correspondence, 1940-2010; 2008-S-0019 (Box 34)
  - College essays, 1935-1939; 2008-S-0019 (Box 34)
  - Herschberger essays on Kinsey Reports, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 34)
  - Artciles, fliers, miscellaneous materials, 1980-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 35)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1949; 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 35)
  - Bills and bank statements, 1990-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 35)
  - Unidentified photographs, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 35)
  - Advertisements for :"Adam's Rib", undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 35)
  - Play scripts, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 35)
  - Correspondence, 1950-2009; 2008-S-0019 (Box 36)
  - Personal medical information, 2000-2009; 2008-S-0019 (Box 36)
  - Bank statements, 2005-2006; 2008-S-0019 (Box 36)
  - Memorabilia including a ring, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 36)
  - Literary catalogs and materials pertaining to publishing boadsides, 1960-1969; 2008-S-0019 (Box 36, Box 37)
  - Unidentified photographs, 1960-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 37)
  - Ninety labeled and unlabeled audio cassettes, 1972-1978; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 38)
  - Thirty-four labeled and unlabeled videocassettes, 1986-1993; 2008-S-0019 (Box 39)
  - Typescript and notes for "A Child's Anthology", undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 40)
  - Herschberger correspondence to mother and family, 1940-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 40, Box 41)
  - Herschberger correspondence from mother, 1940-1959; 2008-S-0019 (Box 41)
  - Photographs and negatives of unidentified people and events, 1960-1980; 2008-S-0019 (Box 42)
  - Photograph album of unidentified people and events, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 43)
  - Thirteen open reel tapes including "Biil's recording of me" and 1956 "Private reading at Poet's Theatre", 1956 March 7; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 43)
  - Ten audiocassette tapes including "Watergate," "Nixon night, "Sergi and me", 1971-1978; undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 43)
  - Correspondence with mother and others, 1940-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 44)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 44)
  - Self help and other books by various authors, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 44, Box 45)
  - Herschberger drafts and typescripts of poems, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 44)
  - Theatre programs, 1940-1959; 2008-S-0019 (Box 44)
  - Tax information and miscellaneous bills, 1960-1999; 2008-S-0019 (Box 45)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1949; 2008-S-0019 (Box 45)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1980-1989; 2008-S-0019 (Box 45)
  - Small metal file cabinet locked with no key, undated; 2008-S-0019 (Box 46)
- Ruth Herschberger diaries, poems, photographs and miscellaneous materials, 1970-2001; 2008-S-0008; 0,75 linear feet
  Separated Materials
  Diaries 1976, 1980 and 2001 were added to diaries in Acc. 08S-19
  Pollet, Elizabeth
  - Photographs of Herschberger and other subjects, 1970-1989; 2008-S-0090 (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Clippings, notes and miscellaneous papers, 1980-2009; 2008-S-0090 (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Drafts of Poems, undated; 2008-S-0090 (Box 1, Box 2)